<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-05-07T23:54:47+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Final Project Group 34</title><subtitle>Impact of Urban Reforestation on Melbourne urban area </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Is Melbourne getting too hot? Part I</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/07/post1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Is Melbourne getting too hot? Part I" /><published>2024-05-07T05:45:13+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-07T05:45:13+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/07/post1</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/07/post1.html"><![CDATA[<p>Global warming has been a known threat for long time. It is common knowledge that urban areas are heating up. When in metropolitan areas building are built close together, they trap the heat, which leads to an increase of the surrounding temperatures.</p>

<p>Big metropolitan areas like Melbourne, which count a population of over 5 million people can become unbearable to live in. This is caused by a phenomenon known as the <a href="https://www.epa.gov/heatislands"> <strong>Heat Island Effect</strong></a>, where urban areas have a saturation of heat and exhibit higher temperatures than surrounding areas. This is due to buildings, roads and other infrastructure absorbing more heat than natural bodies such as forests, for example in summer time walking barefeet on asphalt road will burn you while walking on grass will be fine. In heavily populated areas the hot air can find some difficulties to escape and temperature can boost up. Let’s observe the graph of the mean temperature from year 1910 to 2022 in Olympic Park Melbourne.</p>

<p><img src="/img_post/temp.png" alt="tempraise" /></p>

<p>Olympic Park Melbourne is an area in the inner city not surrounded by a lot of building. However, as you can see from the graph the temperature mean went up during the year. The reader might notice some bumps in the graph. An interesting one is the peak between 2000 and 2020. Those peaks where exactly registered in 2009 and 2014. <a href="https://knowledge.aidr.org.au/resources/health-heatwave-south-eastern-australia-2009/">The January 2009</a> heatwave in Victoria was an event that entered history books because it was of an unprecedented intensity, as you might notice from the peak, and duration with maximum temperature of 15 celsius above average.</p>

<p>Is there a solution to global warming? For sure there is and they have been largely discussed over and over but in the meantime the world keeps spinning and living in the center of a big city can become unsustainable. What is that make you relief from the sun? Where people can find refuge in extreme heat ?  Shadow, you will look for shadow. There have been many proven and successful studies suggesting that trees and other foliage promotes cooler environments through shade and evapotranspiration. This leads also <a href="https://www.epa.gov/heatislands/using-trees-and-vegetation-reduce-heat-islands">many other benefits</a> such as less weight on the health system through reduction of heat related illnesses, improved air quality and reduced energy consumption. It can be proved in the graph below that for district with more trees canopies the health rating is higher. It is interesting how for 3004 postal code the health rating is low despite it is one of the are with the most trees.</p>

<p><img src="/img_post/health.png" alt="tempraise" /> Fig 1. - Show the percentage of the report regarding health in percentage for the categories displayed on the left for 2022.</p>

<p>Melbourne administration understood the vital role of urban reforestation to face climate change. <a href="https://www.natureaustralia.org.au/newsroom/living-melbourne/">A healthy urban forest</a> will play a critical role in maintaining the health and liveability of Melbourne. They are aiming to increase canopy cover from 22 per cent to 40 per cent by 2040.</p>

<iframe width="140%" height="800" src="/html/heatmap_2021.html"></iframe>
<p>Map 1. -Tree canopy distribution.</p>

<p>The heatmaps from 2014 to 2016 demonstrate relatively minor changes in canopy distribution in Melbourne, correlating with the closeness in sample sizes during these years. The heatmaps reveal that while central and northwestern Melbourne consistently show dense canopy coverage, the outer areas exhibit less coverage. Conversely, despite the similarity in sample sizes between 2013 and 2019, the heatmaps display vastly different results. This discrepancy can be attributed to the differences in data representation: in 2013, tree canopies were recorded using multipolygon shapes, whereas in 2019, they were represented with simpler polygon shapes. Such changes in data structure could significantly impact the visual and statistical interpretation of canopy coverage</p>

<p>From the heatmap, it’s hard to see the increment of tree density from 2019 to 2021 which indicate the growing of tree is slow, but from the Bar plot below, the total area indeed increased.</p>

<p>In conclusion, while Melbourne has made significant strides towards enhancing its urban forest, the city still faces hurdles in achieving its canopy cover goals. Continued efforts and adherence to the urban reforestation strategy are crucial for reaching these targets and maintaining Melbourne’s status as one of the world’s most liveable cities.</p>

<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <title>Document</title>
</head>
<body>
    <!-- Image insertion -->
    <img src="/img_post/sample&amp;area.png" alt="Descriptive text about the image" width="900" height="300" />
    <p>Fig 1. - Canopy areas to temperature relation sorted by postcode. </p>
</body>
</html>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Global warming has been a known threat for long time. It is common knowledge that urban areas are heating up. When in metropolitan areas building are built close together, they trap the heat, which leads to an increase of the surrounding temperatures.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The impact trees have on urban temperature - Part II</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/07/post2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The impact trees have on urban temperature - Part II" /><published>2024-05-07T05:44:13+02:00</published><updated>2024-05-07T05:44:13+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/05/07/post2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/05/07/post2.html"><![CDATA[<p>With all that doom and gloom is there hope to mitigate some of these effects by creating more dense urban forests in Melbourne? Using the <a href="https://data.melbourne.vic.gov.au/explore/dataset/tree-canopies-2021-urban-forest/information/?location=15,-37.79968,144.96604&amp;basemap=mbs-7a7333">Tree Canopy survey from 2021</a> we are able to have a very accurate overview of Melbournes current state of foliage coverage in the inner suburbs of the city, each tree is surveyed for the area of canopy. This has allowed us to create a nice bar chart that shows the cumulative canopy area of the trees surveyed per suburb, to better normalise the data we have divided it by the total area of the <strong>postcode</strong> that it is in.</p>

<html lang="en">
<head>
    <meta charset="UTF-8" />
    <title>Document</title>
</head>
<body>
    <!-- Image insertion -->
    <img src="/img_post/canopy_area.png" alt="Descriptive text about the image" width="800" height="500" />
    <p>Fig 1. - Canopy areas to temperature relation sorted by postcode. </p>
</body>
</html>

<h3 id="post-codes-a-quick-rundown">Post codes, a quick rundown:</h3>
<p><em>A quick definition of a <strong>postcode</strong>: Melbourne is divided into suburbs, these have a unique name to them, then there are collections of suburbs under one <strong>postcode</strong>, some postcodes contain more suburbs than others.</em></p>

<p>We can see that the suburb with least amount of trees per its area by <em>square meters</em> is <strong>3008</strong> which is accurate as that area is known as the Docklands which is a new development containing a port. While on the opposite spectrum we can see the postcode <strong>3052</strong> which is North Melbourne/Parkville which contains many parks and the zoo and very intuitively many trees.</p>

<h3 id="soil-sensors-a-quick-rundown">Soil sensors, a quick rundown:</h3>
<p><em>Before investigating the relationship between temperature and trees it would be wise to define the sensor data we have used to accumulate the temperature information. Melbourne has a comprehensive network of smart soil sensors. These sensors are more immune from the impact of random variables like a car window reflecting light at a sensor heating it up, or a car engine idling near a sensor compared to their atmospheric counterpart.</em></p>

<p>Linking the two datasets together allows us to investigate whether it is true that trees reduce the average temperature in an urban environment. Looking at the two postcode extremes <strong>3008</strong> and <strong>3052</strong> the temperature values are quite close both almost 16 degrees celcius, however <strong>3052</strong> has significantly more trees, why is this? As with all environmental data there can be many variables to consider, however in this case the biggest one would be that <strong>3008</strong> is on a large water front, this means that it will in general experience <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/15/16/12537">more wind and lower temperatures than the inland</a> <strong>3052</strong>. Regardless as a testament to the theory, <strong>3053</strong> is an inland postcode next to <strong>3052</strong> and it contains less than half the canopy coverage than <strong>3052</strong> and has a much higher temperature average than <strong>3052</strong>. This means that the increased canopy coverage has similar effects to reduction of temperatures as a waterfront area! Finally, we will just bring our attention to the postcodes next to each other and inland in a belt, this would be <strong>3000-3052</strong> (the last 4 bars of the plot). Here we can clearly see a decreasing trend in temperature from the LOESS (locally estimated scatterplot smoothing) line, while we have increasing tree canopy coverage. Fantastic, so YES tree canopy does reduce average temperature in urban environments - well, we should hold our horses here a little. Some things to consider before taking this as factual evidence, the sensor density might be higher in some postcodes than others and sensors might be placed in more favourable locations than others (they are microclimate sensitive). To be able to give a more concrete answer we would have to get many more sensors and spread them out evenly throughout our suburbs. However, for our preliminary analysis this gives us a good direction and indication that this is a possible direction for Melbourne to take to reduce the impacts of climate change.</p>

<h1 id="can-trees-reduce-the-severity-of-weather-events">Can trees reduce the severity of weather events?</h1>

<iframe width="140%" height="800" src="/html/bokeh_variation_temp.html"></iframe>
<p>Fig 2. -Average of the sensor data per postcode over two days during April</p>

<p>Reducing average temperatures is one thing, but stablising highly volatile weather events where temperatures can swing wildly is another important factor to investigate. Large swings in weather and temperature can lead a population to shorter lifespans, because <a href="https://www.nih.gov/news-events/nih-research-matters/summer-temperature-swings-linked-shorter-lifespan">large fluctuations in temperature during summer boost the risk of death</a> in older people, very young and people with chronic diseases. To give people a fair chance at life in our changing climate once again <strong>we must</strong> look for solutions to reduce the severity of turbulent weather events. <a href="https://pure.manchester.ac.uk/ws/portalfiles/portal/54524206/FULL_TEXT.PDF">Trees offer the possibility to offset this, and increase general human comfort</a>.</p>

<p>To see if this is working out in Melbourne we plot the average of the sensor data per postcode over two days during April. This way we can see if some postcodes see not only reductions in overall temperature but if the curves are less volatile giving us idication that shifts in weather will also be slowed down. Now that we know which postcodes are the most green, we will investigate <strong>3052</strong> and compare it to the fluctuation in <strong>3006</strong>. We can see that <strong>3006</strong> experience both higher temperatures but also a slightly larger spike with rising temperature, giving us maybe an insight that the area is less resistant to the changing temperature. I urge the reader to interact with the plot and see the relation of change in temperature and canopy area, to see if there some immunity to strong fluctuations. <em>It is to be noted</em> that due to the sparcity of some of the areas, it is not possible to make a definitive conclusion on this hypothesis when cumulatively comparing the sensors.</p>

<iframe width="140%" height="800" src="/html/soil_sensor_canopy_density_map.html"></iframe>
<p>Fig 3. - Timeseries showing the temperature of areas for the year 2022. Scroll the slider on the top left and notice how the temperature sensors closed to the water have less temperature oscillations.</p>

<p>Therefore we will investigate through the power of <em>one more</em> visualisation by harnessing the beauty of geospatial data and maps! By doing so we can plot each sensor (that is at a 10-20cm depth) individually to visually demonstrate how temperatures can fluctuate more rapidly in localised areas with less tree canopy which is show as a heatmap. Drag the timeslider around on the map, this is moving the sensor data in thirty minute increments over a three month period from March to June, the more flickering that occurs in some areas will show more susceptibility to temperature change (which is bad!).</p>

<p>To aid in the discussion I have marked <em>three notable areas</em> with red circles. Drawing attention to marker 1, which is in a high tree density area here we can see the changes to be more gradual and inline with general changing of the overall temperature. This in comparison to sensors located in marker 3 which is in a very urban area in the CBD with little trees experiences, flicker significantly more giving us some visual indication that it has less thermal buffering capacity, and therefor less resilience to more severe temperature fluctuations. It is also important to discuss outliers and external factors that may sway our visual analysis. Looking at marker 2, these sensors also flicker a lot more, and this is because they are on the famous Princes Bridge, and as discussed more being so close to an open body of water will lead to greater temperature changes due to evaporation and wind. So while looking at the sensors in a more localised and individual manner can give us greater insights it can be more prone to be impacted by local external variables that have to be considered.</p>

<p>To conclude, through our data driven journey of trying to uncover the power of trees in an urban environment we have managed to hopefully convince you as a reader that there is some indication that creating greater and more dense swathes of trees in urban environments can be a tool to help Melbournians secure a more certain future in times where uncertainty rings loudly. This also is not localised to Victoria or even Australia, this sort of evidence should be used to convince all people globally in a position to do so to act and put more funding into simple and cost effective solutions such as greenifying our concreted areas.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[With all that doom and gloom is there hope to mitigate some of these effects by creating more dense urban forests in Melbourne? Using the Tree Canopy survey from 2021 we are able to have a very accurate overview of Melbournes current state of foliage coverage in the inner suburbs of the city, each tree is surveyed for the area of canopy. This has allowed us to create a nice bar chart that shows the cumulative canopy area of the trees surveyed per suburb, to better normalise the data we have divided it by the total area of the postcode that it is in.]]></summary></entry></feed>